Guide to the Ernest Hemingway Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ernest Hemingway collection
1920-1962
YCAL MSS 199
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.96
(6 boxes) + 1 art object
The Hemingway collection consists of letters, manuscripts, photographs and artwork related to Ernest Hemingway. There are original letters and copies of letters from Hemingway to Grace Quinlan Otis, Edward K. Thompson and others. Writings include a photocopy of a typescript draft of "A Moveable Feast," a typescript draft of "Today is Friday," a galley proof of "A Hemingway Reader," and galley proofs of manuscripts by Carlos Baker, Charles A. Fenton, Leicester Hemingway, Lillian Ross, Marcelline Hemingway Sanford and Philip Young. There are also photographs of Hemingway as a young man and representations of Hemingway in artwork by Arthur Hawkins and Justin Sturm.
Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Ernest Hemingway Collection was acquired through various gifts and purchases dating from 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Ernest Hemingway Collection consists of letters, manuscripts, photographs, and artwork documenting the life and work of Ernest Hemingway. The collection spans the years 1920-1960.
The collection is housed in 6 boxes and organized into four series according to provenance: James T. Babb Gift and Bequest, Book of the Month Club Gifts, Grace Quinlan Otis Gifts, and Material from Other Sources. Boxes 4-6 contain Oversize material.
Series I, James T. Babb Gift and Bequest, consists of three letters, one manuscript, and a bust of Hemingway by Justin Sturm. There are two typescript letters from Hemingway, with autograph corrections, and one third-party letter from editor Alan Jackson to James T. Babb. Hemingway's letter to "Miss Finch," dated August 18, 1926, accompanies a corrected typescript manuscript of the story "Today is Friday." In the letter Hemingway thanks Finch for a copy of Gertrude Stein's "Descriptions of Literature," which he describes as "one of the best things of Stein's that I have ever read."
Series II, Book of the Month Club Gifts, consists of writings by Hemingway and by others. Writings by Hemingway include a galley proof of A Hemingway Reader and a typescript photocopy, with proofreaders' marks, of A Moveable Feast. There are galley proofs for secondary literature on Hemingway by Carlos Baker, Charles Fenton, Leicester Hemingway, John McCaffery, Lillian Ross, and Philip Young. There is also a typescript carbon manuscript of Marcelline Hemingway Sanford's At the Hemingways. Writings are arranged alphabetically by author.
Series III, Grace Quinlan Otis Gifts, housed in box 2, consists of original letters from Hemingway to Grace Quinlan Otis, photographs of Hemingway circa 1920, and a print of Hemingway by Arthur Hawkins. There are 10 letters and one card from Hemingway to Otis, a childhood friend in Michigan, dating from 1920-21. Letters, signed "Stein," are personal in nature.
Series IV, Material from Other Sources, housed in box 3, includes copies of letters from Hemingway to Bill Rogers and Edward K. Thompson, a galley proof of To Have and Have Not, and microfilm for The Co-Operative Commonwealth.
Oversize material, housed in boxes 4-6, contains material from Series II and Series IV.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors; Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968; Baker, Carlos, 1909-1987; Fenton, Charles A., 1919-1960; Hawkins, Arthur, 1903-; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Hemingway, Leicester, 1915-1982; Otis, Grace Quinlan; Ross, Lillian, 1918-2017; Sanford, Marcelline Hemingway, 1898-1963; Sturm, Justin; Thompson, Edward K., 1907-; Young, Philip, 1918-1991; Book-of-the-Month Club
- James T. Babb Gift and Bequest, 1926-1934; Series I; 4
  Scope and Contents
  Gifts of James T. Babb and Estate, 1939-1976
  - TLS, with autograph corrections, from EH to James T. Babb, [1930] Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - TLS, with autograph corrections, from EH to "Miss Finch", 1926 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes typescript manuscript, corrected, for "Today is Friday"
  - TLS from Alan Jackson to James T. Babb, 1930 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bronze bust of EH by Justin Sturm, 1934 (Box ART, Folder 4)
- Book of the Month Club Gift, 1950-1962; Series II; 9
  Gifts of the Book of the Month Club, 1951
  - Baker, Carlos
    - Hemingway: The Writer as Artist, galley proof, [ca. 1952] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fenton, Charles A.
    The Apprenticeship of Ernest Hemingway
    - Galley proof, [ca. 1954] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Book jacket, [ca. 1954] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hemingway, Ernest
    - A Hemingway Reader, galley proof, [ca. 1953]
    - A Moveable Feast
      - Typescript photocopy, with proofreaders' marks, [ca. 1960] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Report by Clifton Fadiman, galley proof
  - Hemingway, Leicester
    - My Brother, Ernest Hemingway, galley proof, [ca. 1962] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - McCaffery, John K. M.
    - Ernest Hemingway, the Man and His Work, galley proof, [ca. 1950] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ross, Lillian
    - Portrait of Hemingway, galley proof, [ca. 1961] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sanford, Marcelline Hemingway
    - At the Hemingways: A Family Portrait, typescript carbon, corrected, [ca. 1962] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Young, Philip
    - Ernest Hemingway, galley proof, [ca. 1952] (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Grace Quinlan Otis Gifts, 1920-1921; Series III; 3
  Gifts of Grace Quinlan Otis, 1962-1963
  - 5 ALS, 5 TLS and 1 signed card from EH to Grace Quinlan Otis, 1920-21 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Ernest Hemingway, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Print of EH by Arthur Hawkins, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Material from Other Sources, 1920-1960; Series IV; 3
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources. Sources indicated on individual folders.
  - Typescript carbon copy of letter from EH to Bill Rogers, 1948 Jul 29 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photographic copy of ALS from EH to [Edward K.] Thompson, 1960 Jun 2 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - To Have and Have Not, galley proof
  - The Co-Operative Commonwealth, microfilm, 1920 Sep (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Oversize, 1953-1960; 4.92; (3 boxes)
  - A Hemingway Reader galley proof (In Series II), [ca. 1953] (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Clifton Fadiman report (In Series II), [1960?] (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - To Have and Have Not galley proof (In Series IV) (Box 6, Folder 22)